<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>external-blog on Jason Downing</title>
    <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/tags/external-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in external-blog on Jason Downing</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jasondowning.github.io/tags/external-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>5 steps to plan your launch</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-5-steps-to-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-5-steps-to-launch/</guid>
      <description>You can only launch once, so do it right
With PalmPay live in Nigeria and Ghana live and 4 more African markets in-flight, here are some lessons from my experience over the last 2 years.
1. Do your research I know this might appear obvious, but understanding the market landscape before you start gives you the power to make better long term decisions.
Spending time early on to get this right will direct your strategy and give your project plan a strong foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running remote teams</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-running-remote-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-running-remote-teams/</guid>
      <description>The new normal is here - run your remote team well and continue to build excellent products
With experience managing remote teams over the last 5 years, here are my cheat notes to ensure you remain productive whilst still having harmony.
Build your business rhythm We are all creatures of habit. Building habits into your team helps with productivity and alignment. Your team will know where to be and what to expect from the important meetings week in and out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiring the best remotely: a checklist</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-remote-hiring-ticklist-/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-remote-hiring-ticklist-/</guid>
      <description>There is so much talent out there, you just need to find it
I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with remote teams across Africa, Europe, America and Asia and have been hiring remote product teams over the last 3 years. Here are is a checklist to help
Know what you want (and write it down) You are the hiring manager! It is your role to shape the macro and micro aspects of the role.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>