<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>external-blog on Jason Downing</title>
    <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/tags/external-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in external-blog on Jason Downing</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jasondowning.github.io/tags/external-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Card issuing &amp; program management - a synopsis</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2021-02-becoming-a-card-issuer1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2021-02-becoming-a-card-issuer1/</guid>
      <description>Thinking about becoming a program manager? Think carefully...
Setting up a card issuing business line requires collaboration and careful business modeling.
The setup: becoming a Program Manager To issue cards you need to play in two regulatory spaces - firstly within the central bank&amp;rsquo;s regulations and secondly within the card scheme regulations. Depending on the country there are different roles which will be played out by each institution. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that your company will partner with a bank to launch the card product.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tales from the loop: hacking with the Gates Foundation open source payment’s switch</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2021-01-tales-from-the-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2021-01-tales-from-the-loop/</guid>
      <description>Repost from January 15th 2021. The original article is on PalmPay.co
Introduction Two weeks ago, a small team of adventurers from PalmPay joined the Mojaloop hackathon which was organised by DSF Labs on behalf of the Gates Foundation. Wow, that sentence needs explaining! Let’s get some background.
The Gates Foundation and others believe that one part of the financial inclusion problem is due to the limits of existing payments infrastructure. With an aim to improve inclusion they started an open-source project called Mojaloop in 1997.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building your Standard Operating Procedure</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-building-your-sop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 11:23:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-building-your-sop/</guid>
      <description>Great services are build by amazing teams and strong processes
Know your Standard Operating Procedure How will you know what to improve if you don&amp;rsquo;t understand the operational model of your business?
A Standard Operating Procedure (SOP) is a collection of all the processes within your business. This is just a fancy way of saying you know how your business operates.
Encourage each department to make their own process list - ultimately each team is responsible for their own activities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 steps to plan your launch</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-5-steps-to-launch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-5-steps-to-launch/</guid>
      <description>You can only launch once, so do it right
With PalmPay live in Nigeria and Ghana live and 4 more African markets in-flight, here are some lessons from my experience over the last 2 years.
1. Do your research I know this might appear obvious, but understanding the market landscape before you start gives you the power to make better long term decisions.
Spending time early on to get this right will direct your strategy and give your project plan a strong foundation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running remote teams</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-running-remote-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-running-remote-teams/</guid>
      <description>The new normal is here - run your remote team well and continue to build excellent products
With experience managing remote teams over the last 5 years, here are my cheat notes to ensure you remain productive whilst still having harmony.
Build your business rhythm We are all creatures of habit. Building habits into your team helps with productivity and alignment. Your team will know where to be and what to expect from the important meetings week in and out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiring the best remotely: a checklist</title>
      <link>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-remote-hiring-ticklist-/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jasondowning.github.io/posts/2020-08-remote-hiring-ticklist-/</guid>
      <description>There is so much talent out there, you just need to find it
I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with remote teams across Africa, Europe, America and Asia and have been hiring remote product teams over the last 3 years. Here are is a checklist to help
Know what you want (and write it down) You are the hiring manager! It is your role to shape the macro and micro aspects of the role.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>